Guide to Manuscripts in the Albi Rosenthal Collection of Monteverdi and the Birth of Opera
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Manuscripts in the Albi Rosenthal collection of Monteverdi and the birth of opera
1579-1966
1612-1670
Monteverdi 2
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.2
(1 box)
Manuscripts in the Albi Rosenthal Collection of Monteverdi and the Birth of Opera consist of letters, writings, and music relating to Monteverdi and others involved in the creation of opera in seventeenth-century Italy. Letters of Monteverdi collaborators Claudio Achillini, Jacopo Peri, Ottavio Rinuccini, and other musicians and writers, addressed to third parties or unidentified recipients, concern Monteverdi's music and other music subjects. Other materials include a volume of holograph music by Alessandro Capece and two manuscripts by unidentified writers giving contempory accounts of music performed in seventeenth-century Urbino. Also present are letters of twentieth-century composers Paul Hindemith, Vincent d'Indy, and Gian Francesco Malipiero, concerning Monteverdi's music. Some items are accompanied by notes of former owners, vendor descriptions, transcriptions, or translations, some possibly by French musicologist Henry Prunières.
Rosenthal, Albi, 1914-2004
Capece, Alessandro, 1575?-
Prunières, Henry, 1886-1942
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Sotheby's on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, Hazel M. Osborn Fund, and James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical Notes
Albi Rosenthal (1914-2004), English antiquarian music dealer.
Claudio Monteverdi (1567-1643), Italian composer.
Scope and Contents
Manuscripts in the Albi Rosenthal Collection of Monteverdi and the Birth of Opera consist of letters, writings, and music relating to Monteverdi and others involved in the creation of opera in seventeenth-century Italy. Letters of Monteverdi collaborators Claudio Achillini, Jacopo Peri, Ottavio Rinuccini, and other musicians and writers, addressed to third parties or unidentified recipients, concern Monteverdi's music and other music subjects. Other materials include a volume of holograph music by Alessandro Capece and two manuscripts by unidentified writers giving contempory accounts of music performed in seventeenth-century Urbino. Also present are letters of twentieth-century composers Paul Hindemith, Vincent d'Indy, and Gian Francesco Malipiero, concerning Monteverdi's music. Some items are accompanied by notes of former owners, vendor descriptions, transcriptions, or translations, some possibly by French musicologist Henry Prunières
Arrangement
Organized in one series.
Festivals -- Italy -- Urbino; Madrigals, Italian -- 17th century; Opera -- 17th century; Opera -- Italy -- 17th century; Urbino (Italy) -- Social life and customs; Achillini, Claudio, 1574-1640; Andreini, Francesco, approximately 1548-1624; Buonamente, Giovanni Battista, -1642; Capece, Alessandro, 1575?-; Colonna, Giovanni Paolo, 1637-1695; Doni, Gio. Battista (Giovanni Battista), 1593 or 1594-1647; Goretti, Antonio, ca. 1570-1649; Guarini, Battista, 1538-1612; Hindemith, Paul, 1895-1963; Indy, Vincent d', 1851-1931; Lazzarini, Gregorio, d. 1686; Malipiero, Gian Francesco, 1882-1973; Mazarin, Jules, 1602-1661; Medici, Giovan Carlo de', 1611-1663; Medici, Leopoldo de', 1617-1675; Monteverdi, Claudio, 1567-1643; Peri, Jacopo, 1561-1633; Prunières, Henry, 1886-1942; Rinuccini, Ottavio, 1562-1621; Rosenthal, Albi, 1914-2004; Rosenthal, Albi, 1914-2004 -- Ownership
- Manuscripts, 1579-1966; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Achillini, Claudio (1574-1640). Autograph letter, signed, Bologna, to an unidentified recipient, 1627 August 4; 1 page, folio (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Asking for help in order to allow him to devote himself to writing, and informing the recipient that he is sending him a very able young man to accomplish a task for him in Ferrara
    Biographical/Historical note
    Achillini was the librettist of Monteverdi's Mercurio e Marte (Parma, 1628)
  - Buonamente, Giovanni Battista (d.1642). Autograph letter, signed, Vienna, to Prince Cesare Gonzaga, 1627 March 17; 1 page, 4to (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Asking Gonzaga to help him acquire a violin that had been bought for him in Cremona, emphasizing the high quality of the instrument and its good condition; he also reports composing sonatas for solo violin for the Prince
    Buonamente dedicated several works to Monteverdi and probably played under his direction
  - Capece, Alessandro (d.after 1635). Music, holograph, circa 1617-1624; Bound in contemporary vellum boards; painted arms on cover [Sulmona (Abruzzi)];; 24 pages, 4to (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contains three dialogues for two voices and continuo: La fede e la speranza, for bass and alto; Venere et Arione, for soprano and tenor, and Armida e Rinaldo, for soprano and tenor; and a madrigal, Morte soccorsa, for solo voice and continuo
    Dedication, signed, to Marc-Antonio Borghese, Prince of Sulmona
    Capece was maestro di cappella at Ferrara, Rieti (1616), Sulmona (1617-1624) and Tivoli (1624-1627)
  - Colonna, Giovanni Paolo (1637-1695). Autograph letter, signed, Bologna, to an unidentified recipient, [1679?] November 25; 1 page, 4to, integral blank (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Enclosing part of an opera (not present) and discussing an opera project
    Colonna was the leading composer of sacred and secular dramas of the Bolognese school
  - Doni, Gio. Battista (Giovanni Battista) (1593 or 4-1647). Notes, holograph, undated; 3 sheets (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes notes about Monteverdi's madrigals of 1621, and "operette del Monteverde"
    Accompanied by an autograph letter from an unidentifed writer to Doni, about a music library
    Doni was the first major historian of early Baroque opera
  - Goretti, Antonio (circa 1570-1649). Autograph letter, signed, Ferrara, to an unidentified recipient, 1629 April 18; 3 pages, folio (Box 1, Folder 6)
    About his Mass for two seven-part choirs, describing the accompaniment of four violins, and four wind instruments, violone and organ
    Goretti was Monteverdi's assistant during preparations for Mercurio e Marte in 1628
    See A. Rosenthal, Obiter Scripta, p. 202 and 208, where the letter is illustrated
  - Guarini, Battista (1538-1612). Autograph letter, signed, Rome, to Ludovico Ariosto, 1612 February 29; 1 page, folio, integral address leaf (Box 1, Folder 7)
    About Petrarch and Virgil
    Guarini was the author of the commedia L'Idropica, for which Monteverdi composed a musical prologue in 1608
  - Hindemith, Paul (1895-1963). Autograph letter, signed, to an unidentified recipient, [1958?]; 2 pages, 8vo (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Giving advice on preparation and performance of Monteverdi's madrigal Lagrime d'un amante (1614)
    Letterhead of the Grand Hotel, Rome
  - Indy, Vincent d' (1851-1931). Three autograph letters, signed, Florence, Boffres (Ardèche), and Paris, to unidentified recipients, 1907-1916; 6 pages (Box 1, Folder 9)
    About Monteverdi's Orfeo
  - Lazzarini, Gregorio (d. 1686). Autograph letter, signed, Parma, to an unidentified recipient, 1627 November 26; 1 page, folio (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Probably to Monteverdi's patron Marchese Bentivoglio, about the part of Diana in Monteverdi's Mercurio e Marte, expressing regret that his best scene has been taken out
    Lazzarini was a castrato
  - Malipiero, Gian Francesco (1882-1973). Four autograph letters, signed, Asolo, to Henri Prunières, 1927-1930; 6 pages (Box 1, Folder 11)
    About Monteverdi's Lamento d'Arianna, Il combattimento di Tancredi e Clorinda, and Ballo dell'ingrate
    Malpiero was a composer and musicologist, and an editor of Monteverdi's music
  - Mazarin, Jules (1602-1661). Letter, signed, Paris, to Giovanni Battista Doni, Florence, 1647 August 23; 1 page, folio, integral address leaf (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Thanking him for sending a copy of his book; the letter dates from the year of publication of Doni's book De praestantia musica vetera tres (Florence, 1647)
  - Medici, Giovan Carlo de' (1611-1663). Autograph letter, signed, Florence, to Giovanni Battista Doni, Rome, 1636 May 30; 1 page, folio, integral address leaf (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Thanking Doni for sending him a copy of his book, Compendio del trattato de' generi et de' modi
  - Medici, Leopoldo de' (1617-1675). Autograph letter, signed, Siena, to Giovanni Battista Doni, Rome, 1636 May 21; 1 page, folio, integral blank (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Thanking Dona for sending him a copy his book, Compendio del trattato de' generi et de' modi
  - Peri, Jacopo (1561-1633). Autograph letter, signed, Florence, to Tommaso Ginori, 1631 Septembe r 11; 1 page, folio, integral autograph address leaf, remains of red seal (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Thanking and repaying him for a loan, and assuring him that if he finds that there is anything left outstanding, he will send that immediately, and conveying to him the best wishes of his father
    Peri was the composer of the earliest opera for which complete music is extant
  - Rinuccini, Ottavio (1562-1621). Autograph letter, signed, to Giulio Faggi, Florence, 1594 September 15; 1 page, folio, integral address leaf (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Explaining why he is unable to assist him and suggesting he ask Alessandro Acciaiuoli
    Rinuccini was librettist of Monteverdi's Arianna and other early operas
  - Unidentified. "Momo. Prologo con la Relatione della Comedia et Intermedij rappresentati in Urbino li 4 di Marzo 1628," manuscript, 21 pages, folio (Box 1, Folder 17)
    With an account of the music by Pietro Gambari, setting intermedii written by Giovanne Leon Semproni for the performance of a comedia by Ottavio d'Isa Capuano
    Gambari is described as a Maestro di Cappella from Urbino
  - Unidentified. Account of a festa, manuscript, early 17th century; 18 pages, folio (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Detailed description of festivities in honour of Archbishop Santoreo of Urbino, with texts of the madrigals and descriptions of instrumental accompaniments
  - Unidentified. Note, manuscript, relating to Francesco Andreini, [1579?]; 1 sheet (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Andreini and his wife Isabella Andreini were commedia dell'arte players, and their son Giovanni Battista Andreini was an actor, dramatist, and poet; music for his La Maddalena was composed by Monteverdi.
  - Other notes of former owners, 19--, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sotheby's list, [2009?] (Box 1, Folder 21)